What do a student in China, an office worker in the UK and an astronaut in space all have in common?
中国的学生、英国的上班族和太空中的宇航员有什么共同点？
They all eat instant noodles.
他们都吃方便面。
And they're not alone – over 100 billion servings of instant noodles are consumed globally each year, making them one of the world's most successful industrial foods.
而且不止他们——全球每年消费超过1000亿份方便面，使其成为全球最成功的工业化食品之一。
But how did this happen?
但这一切是如何发生的呢？
Put simply, they're cheap to produce and cheap to buy, which was exactly what their creator intended.
简单来说，方便面生产成本低、售价便宜，这正是其发明者的初衷。
Momofuku Ando, a Japanese entrepreneur, spent a year perfecting the recipe just after the Second World War.
二战结束后，日本企业家安藤百福花了一年时间完善配方。
He wanted to make something similar to traditional Japanese ramen noodles, while using the wheat flour given to Japan as food aid by the US government.
他想利用美国政府作为粮食援助提供给日本的小麦粉，制作出类似日本传统拉面的食物。
His creation was instantly popular, playing a part in Japan's post-war economic rise.
他的发明一经推出便大受欢迎，为日本战后经济崛起贡献了一份力量。
Even in the year 2000 – according to a poll by the Fuji Research Institute – instant noodles were voted Japan's most successful invention, ahead of high-speed trains, laptops and karaoke.
即便到了2000年，据富士研究所的一项民意调查显示，方便面仍被评为日本最成功的发明，排名高于高铁、笔记本电脑和卡拉OK。
But Japanese people are not alone in their devotion to instant noodles.
并非只有日本人钟爱方便面。
According to the World's Instant Noodles Association, China, Indonesia, Vietnam and India – in that order – all consumed more instant noodles than Japan in 2021.
据世界方便面协会数据，2021年，中国、印度尼西亚、越南、印度（按此顺序）的方便面消费量均超过日本。
Instant noodles' popularity abroad is in part due to how easy they are to adapt to local tastes.
方便面在海外走红，部分原因是它们很容易适配当地口味。
In Thailand, for example, you can get green curry flavour, while in Mexico the noodles are garnished with lime and salsa.
例如在泰国能买到青咖喱味方便面，而在墨西哥，方便面会搭配青柠和萨尔萨辣酱食用。
And it seems that consumers have grown to expect innovation.
消费者似乎也越来越期待产品创新。
Nissin, the food company founded by Ando, launches over 300 products yearly, just in Japan, according to employee Kasura Suzuki.
安藤百福创立的日清食品公司员工铃木香须罗表示，仅在日本，公司每年就推出300多款新产品。
Instant noodles have their critics, too.
方便面也饱受争议。
Their rise in popularity has come at an environmental cost – they're made with palm oil, contributing to deforestation, and their packaging is plastic.
其风靡的背后付出了环境代价——生产使用棕榈油，加剧了森林砍伐，包装也为塑料材质。
And while they are a hot, tasty and filling meal, instant noodles don't have much nutritional value, and include high levels of salt and fat.
尽管方便面热气腾腾、美味饱腹，但营养价值低，且含盐量和脂肪含量极高。
Nevertheless, instant noodles are undoubtedly lifesavers in emergency or extreme situations.
尽管如此，在紧急或极端情况下，方便面无疑是救急的食物。
More than 60 years after their invention, instant noodles have become the default food for anyone short on money, time, or even a kitchen.
方便面问世60多年后，已然成为所有缺钱、缺时间，甚至没有厨房的人的首选食物。